בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is צ"ז tzadi zayin 97.
We are about to hit triple digits. And we pick up, well,
we actually pick up with the first line, but we will reread
the משנה mishna from the bottom of צ"ו עמוד ב', tzadi vav
amud bet, and we are dealing with the whole issue about cooking
in a pot and מריקה ושטיפה, merika u'shtifa, the rinsing and the
scalding, and etc. And
so let's take a look here. Okay, and let's the whole fascinating
discussion about kashering pottery etc. etc.
Okay, so now the משנה mishna says the following of צ"ו עמוד
ב': tzadi vav amud bet: רבי טרפון אומר, Rabbi Tarfon omer, Rabbi
Tarfon says, בישלו מתחילת הרגל יבשלו בו כל הרגל, bishlo mit'chilat haregel
yivashlo bo kol haregel, that normally you have to, we assume you
have to do this scalding, or if it's pottery, you have to
break it the next morning, when the, had you been dealing with
the meat, the meat would become נותר. notar. If it's שלמים, shelamim,
maybe you'll have until the night or whatever, but certainly, you know,
by as a general rule, the next day or certainly, you know,
two days after. And here he says that you don't have to
worry about it the entire רגל, regel, which is a very strange
idea. וחכמים אומרים עד זמן אכילה, V'chachamim omrim ad z'man achila, no,
once it gets to be the time of eating, you have to
do this process. So that's a little bit of a strange phrase.
Some of the גירסא girsa כל זמן אכילה, kol z'man achila, which
means that while it's the time of eating you don't have to
worry about the scalding and the breaking, but after the זמן z'man
of eating is over, meaning after the meat would become נותר, notar,
that's when you would have to do this. Now מריקה ושטיפה. merika
u'shtifa. Now you have to do מריקה ושטיפה. merika u'shtifa. מריקה כמריקת
הכוס ושטיפה כשטיפת הכוס, Merika k'merikat hakos u'shtifa k'shtifat hakos, like you
would rinse a cup, and it's not exactly clear so what's the
difference between מריקה merika and שטיפה? shtifa? רש"י Rashi says that the
מריקה merika is on the outside and the שטיפה shtifa is on
the, I mean מריקה's merika on the inside, the שטיפה's shtifa on
the outside.
מריקה ושטיפה בצונן, Merika u'shtifa b'tzonen, and they're both cold, as we
will see in the גמרא. gemara. Therefore, this approach understands that there
are two rinsings that are cold, and the rinsing of kashering, not
the rinsing, the process of kashering isn't mentioned in the Torah, isn't
mentioned, and that is taken for granted, and that's with scalding with
hot water. השפוד והאסכלה. Hashpud v'ha'askala. Now if you're dealing with a
spit or a grill, so then מגעילן בחמים, mag'ilan b'chamim, so then
those you, it's funny, here we shift from the ritual of מריקה
ושטיפה merika u'shtifa and start using a verb and a language הגעלה,
hag'ala, which is a kashering language. That's interesting thing number one. And
number two is is that it says that you do הגעלה, hag'ala,
whereas we would normally think that what you would do is that
you would do, what do you call it, that you would do,
if it's hot, if it's a grill, it's a spit, you know,
you need to do ליבון, libbun, you would need to kasher directly
over the fire. So all that is quite interesting. Let's see what
the גמרא gemara says. מאי טעמא דרבי טרפון? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Tarfon?
What is the reasoning of Rabbi Tarfon that says that during the
רגל regel you don't have to do this on a daily basis?
דאמר קרא, D'amar kra, the verse says ופנית בבקר והלכת לאהליך, u'fanita
baboker v'halachta l'ohalecha, you shall turn in the morning and go back
to your tent. This is on the רגל. regel. So הכתוב עשאו
לכולן בוקר אחד. hakosev asao l'kulan boker echad. So רש"י Rashi says
that we're somehow assuming that you're not going to do this the
first morning of יום טוב yom tov because maybe your tent isn't,
if you've been עולה לרגל, oleh l'regel, your tent isn't in halakhic
in walking distance, right, you're not allowed to go to your tent
on the first יום טוב yom tov of רגל. regel. So it
means when it's חול המועד. chol hamoed. So once we see it's
the strange sort of way that רש"י Rashi reads it, I mean
it's hard to read the point of the גמרא gemara into the
גמרא, gemara, but once we see that you're not just focused on
the next morning, you're treating the whole period as a day, it
somehow leads to to seeing that you're treating the next two mornings
from now as the next morning. So because only two mornings on
חול המועד chol hamoed can you go back home. So somehow that
leads to the idea that you're treating all of the רגל regel
as one day. All right now it's again exactly not clear how
we get from one to the other. תוספות Tosfot tries to work
it out. But anyway, that's the point. We treat the whole רגל
regel as one day. הכתוב עשאו לכולן בוקר אחד, hakosev asao l'kulan
boker echad, and therefore, if it's all one day, it doesn't sound
like it doesn't become נותר notar until the end of the רגל.
regel. But then the גמרא gemara asks are we really prepared to
stand by that conclusion? So מתקיף לה רב אחדבוי בר אמי, matkif
lah Rav Achadevoi bar Ami, וכי אין פגול ברגל ואין נותר ברגל?
v'chi ein piggul baregel v'ein notar baregel? So really all the רגל
regel is treated as one big day? So if you had a
thought to, you slaughtered something on, you know, one day of the
רגל regel and you had a thought to eat it three days
later, you know, you wouldn't be פגול piggul because it's all halakhically
one day? And are you למעשה l'ma'aseh allowed to eat the meat
the entire רגל, regel, meat that's normally eaten one day? Is that
really true? וכי תימא הכי נמי? V'chi teima hachi nami? That's always
the best, you know, when one man's reductio ad absurdum is another
man's הכי נמי. hachi nami. Okay, maybe you'd say yeah, that's what
Rabbi Tarfon says. No, you can't say that. ותניא רבי נתן אומר
לא אמר רבי טרפון אלא זו בלבד. V'tanya Rabbi Natan omer lo
amar Rabbi Tarfon ela zo bilvad. Rabbi Tarfon only said his הלכה
halakha about the the מריקה merika and the שטיפה shtifa about the
kashering. He didn't say it about the other things, about the actual
eating of the meat. אלא כדירב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Ela
k'd'Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, fine, it's not based on that
that it's all treated one day. It's like the statement of Rav
Nachman דאמר רב נחמן... d'amar Rav Nachman... אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה amar rav nachman amar rabbah bar avuha כל יום ויום
נעשה גיהול לחברו. kol yom vayom naase giul lachaveiro. What happens is
that every day winds up koshering the previous day. So the way
that it works is the following: remember we spoke yesterday, now this
is interesting because we spoke about how from a כשרות kashrus perspective,
not from this ritual perspective, in theory if you're cooking vegetable soup
in your pot, that could be an act of koshering. So what
he is saying is the following: most of the sacrifices you're going
to bring are going to be שלמים. shelamim. שלמים shelamim have two
days of eating. So let's say today I brought a חטאת, chatas,
okay, 10:00 AM on a Monday morning I brought a חטאת. chatas.
Now in theory by the way this is true any day of
the year, but because there are so many שלמים shelamim during the
רגל regel we're just going to assume this is what's going to
happen, okay? So 10:00 AM we bring a חטאת, chatas, 11:00 AM
we bring a שלמים. shelamim. That שלמים shelamim bringing was a הגעלה,
hagala, koshered the pot from the חטאת chatas taste, okay, you with
me? So it koshered the pot from the חטאת chatas taste, so
come tomorrow morning, Tuesday morning, there's not a חיוב chiyuv to do
מריקה ושטיפה merika ushtifa because there's no נותר notar in the pot.
The assumption is that that was koshering, that wasn't the biblical obligation,
the ritual obligation of מריקה ושטיפה, merika ushtifa, but מריקה ושטיפה merika
ushtifa is only obligated once there is נותר notar in the walls
of the pot. So come Tuesday morning and there's no נותר notar
in the walls of the pot. Okay, but what's going to happen?
Come Wednesday morning the שלמים shelamim from Monday will be נותר, notar,
right? אבא, Abba, what are you going to do on Tuesday?
What are you going to do on Tuesday? What are you going
to use the pot for? More שלמים! shelamim! So your Tuesday שלמים
shelamim koshers it from the Monday שלמים, shelamim, okay? And therefore
come Wednesday morning there's not going to be any נותר, notar, there's
just going to be Tuesday שלמים shelamim taste in it, which is
still okay. And then your Wednesday שלמים shelamim is going to kosher
it from your Tuesday שלמים. shelamim. So basically until you stop bringing
so many שלמים, shelamim, okay, if you stop if there's a very
if it's a normal day in the בית המקדש beit hamikdash and
there's only a handful of שלמים shelamim you can't assume
necessarily that you koshered it from yesterday's etc. So that's when you'll
have to start worrying about it. But during the רגל regel there
are just so many שלמים shelamim which give you an extra day
and they kosher it
from the from the stuff that has a clock ticking on it
today, and therefore you're okay. Now of course what that means is
you have to be careful to after a חטאת chatas before the
day is over to bring a שלמים, shelamim, that שלמים shelamim have
to come after a חטאת. chatas. So רש"י Rashi says fine, we're
careful to make sure that that happens, or there's just such a
high proportion of שלמים shelamim that we can just assume it's going
to happen. Yes, Michael?
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon lived post-חורבן? churban? Yes, okay.
Yeah, all this is just is the same way the whole מסכת
masechet is all rabbis who live post-חורבן. churban.
But we had one citation, remember?
Okay, now מריקה כמריקת הכוס שטיפה כשטיפת הכוס. merika k'merikat hakos shtifa
k'shtifat hakos. I'm sorry, I skipped a line. וחכמים אומרים עד זמן
אכילה. vachachamim omrim ad zman achila. The וחכמים vachachamim say no, once
it's the again I'm going to read it the entire either it
means the time the next morning where you begin eating the next
sacrifices or we'll read it with the גירסא girsa כל זמן אכילה,
kol zman achila, as long as it's the time of eating you
don't have to do it, but once the time of eating is
over, once the stuff absorbed in the pot would become נותר, notar,
then you are obligated to do it. מאי קאמר? mai ka’amar? What
does this mean? אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, amar rav
nachman amar rabbah bar avuha, the same רב נחמן אמר רבה בר
אבוה rav nachman amar rabbah bar avuha
said,
ממתין לו עד זמן אכילה mamtin lo ad zman achila or כל
זמן אכילה kol zman achila והדר עביד ליה מריקה ושטיפה. vehadar avid
leh merika ushtifa. So you don't as long as you can keep
the pot,
and maybe you don't and תוספות Tosafos has an interesting point you
might want to say wait, let me try to do this whole
procedure before it becomes נותר, notar, prevent a problem, an ounce of
prevention is worth a pound of cure, but it could be no,
you don't have an obligation and the תורה Torah only mandates this
ritual,
it's once the time has run out, okay? So you go ahead
and you don't do anything with the pot while it's normal time
of eating the meat that was cooked in the pot,
והדר עביד ליה מריקה ושטיפה, vehadar avid leh merika ushtifa, and then
once that time of eating is over and had you been dealing
with the meat the meat would be נותר, notar, that's when you
have this special ritual of, A: you do normal הגעלה, hagala, you
kosher it, and then you do the special ritual of מריקה ושטיפה.
merika ushtifa.
Meaning you have to as opposed to you're allowed?
Right, תוספות Tosafos is basic right, תוספות Tosafos has a little bit
of a question about that but his basic conclusion is you have
to, you're not supposed to do it before the time came.
And you can't use it for another one in the interim because
then you're ממעט זמן אכילה memayet zman achila of the next one.
If I do it, if I have say two days to do
it, then I can't then I can't.
Well we're going to get to that in the next משנה, mishna,
that's a good point. Right, if you cook something else, it would
be a problem about cooking a שלמים shelamim in a חטאת chatas
pot, would that limit the time you can eat the
שלמים, shelamim, right? So that's we're going to get to in the
next משנה. mishna. I mean Michael raised the right question when the
גמרא gemara said before כל יום נעשה גיהול לחברו kol yom naase
giul lachaveiro that's all very good that when you cook a שלמים
shelamim in a חטאת chatas pot it koshers the חטאת chatas pot,
but does that now require you that the שלמים shelamim meat that
absorbed the חטאת chatas taste now you might have to have a
limited... Okay, מנא לן הני מילי, manlan hanei milei, where do you
get this idea that you wait till the time of eating and
then you do it after the time of eating has run out?
אמר רבי יוחנן משום אבא בר יוסי בן אבא, Amar Rabbi Yochanan
mishum Abba bar Yossi ben Abba, כתיב ksiv ומרק ושוטף. umorak veshutaf.
It would be rinsed and whatever, rinsed and washed or you know
scalded and washed depending on what you read in מריקה merika is.
וכתיב uksiv and the next verse says כל זכר בכהנים יאכל אותה.
kol zachar bakohanim yochal osah. Okay, because it's talking generally about the
חטאת, chatas, all males eat it. הא כיצד, ha keitzad, what does
that mean? It means ממתין לה עד זמן אכילה. mamtin lah ad
zman achilah. Again, until the time of eating is funny unless it
means the eating of the next of the next day, the next
day's eating, or it means כל זמן אכילה, kol zman achilah, if
that's our גירסא. girsa. So if it's the rinsing relates to the
fact that כהנים kohanim eat from it, so as long as they're
eating from it you're not doing the rinsing, והדר עביד לה מריקה
ושטיפה, v'hadar avid lah merika ushtifa, and then you do it once
the time of eating is over. Okay, now we get to the
actual procedure
itself. מריקה כמריקת הכוס שטיפה כשטיפת הכוס. merika k'merikas hakos shtifa k'shtifas
hakos. תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan: מריקה ושטיפה בצונן דברי רבי. merika ushtifa
betzonen divrei Rebbi. They're—it's cold, it's just inside and outside. וחכמים אומרים
מריקה בחמין ושטיפה בצונן. v'chachamim omrim merika bachamin ushtifa betzonen. No, מריקה
merika is the hot boiling water, that's the kashering, and שטיפה shtifa
is this extra act of rinsing. As I said to you, this
extra act of rinsing is a particular ritual done in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it's not part of the kashering process, but תוספות
Tosafos points out that the מנהג minhag was to do this as
part of the kashering process. So the actual kashering that we do
is modeled after this, even though not all the components are required.
We also do specifically water, although again הלכה halacha the פוסקים poskim
say in theory vegetable soup could be a kashering, but again based
on the way it was done—besides that it would just be a
waste of good food—but based on the way it was done here
we tend to do it as water. We also tend to, you
know, we also tend to do it as filling up the entire
vessel, not just to the point that the vessel was used. So
all those things we pointed out yesterday that are additional ritual requirements
and not just kashering requirements, as a practice we default to them
even in our process of kashering.
Okay, but anyway—so it's internal and the inside, meaning I don't need
to like put, you know, like the internal walls and those I
put the hot water in it?
Well, yeah, the external, yeah, only if there's a concern that it
splattered. Anyway, so מאי טעמא דרבנן, mai ta'ama d'rabanan, what's the reason
of the רבנן? rabanan? מידי דהוה אגעולי עובדי כוכבים. midei d'hava a'gi'ulei
ovdei kochavim. So the rabbis need to read that one of these
words is referring to the boiling water because you gotta kasher it.
The whole thing is rooted in the fact that it absorbed problematic
taste or it absorbed tastes that are now problematic, so there's got
to be a kashering. רבי אמר לך, Rebbi amar lach, Rebbi will
say to you, הגעלה לא קאמינא. hagalah lo kamina. I'm not talking
about kashering. Kashering is taken for granted. But when the תורה Torah
describes what you do, that's the ritual on top of the kashering.
כי קאמינא למריקה ושטיפה דבתר
הגעלה. ki kamina lemerika ushtifa d'basar hagalah. No, no, I'm talking about
the מריקה merika and שטיפה shtifa that come after הגעלה. hagalah. So
he's more מחמיר. machmir. I understand. Okay, but the way the גמרא's
Gemara reading it is, of course you gotta kasher, in addition there's
this act of ritual of an inside and outside wash. ורבנן אם
כן לכתוב קרא או מורק מורק או שוטף שוטף. v'rabanan im kein
lichtov kra o morak morak o shutaf shutaf. If it was two
washings it would use the same verb. מאי ומרק ושוטף? mai umorak
veshutaf? שמע מינה מריקה בחמין ושטיפה בצונן. shma mina merika bachamin ushtifa
betzonen. Different verbs are telling you that there—one of them, the מריקה,
merika, is with the putting it in boiling water and then there's
this ritual washing.
ורבי, v'Rebbi, Rebbi would say back, no, yes there are different verbs,
but they're different verbs because they're different types of washing. אי כתב
ומרק ומרק, ei kesav umorak umorak, if it said ומרק umorak twice,
הוה אמינא תרי זימני מורק, hava amina srei zimnei morak, או תרי
זימני שוטף. o srei zimnei shutaf. It would either have been that,
you know, two inner washings or two outer washings. להכי כתב ומרק
ושוטף, lehachi kesav umorak veshutaf, לומר לך מריקה כמריקת הכוס שטיפה כשטיפת
הכוס. lomar lach merika k'merikas hakos shtifa k'shtifas hakos. That yes, they're
two different verbs because one is washing on the inside and one
is washing on the outside. But we're not talking here about the
boiling water. Of course I agree to the boiling water, it's just
that that's not what the verse is talking about, the verse is
talking about a ritual. The גמרא Gemara interestingly ignored the whole case
of the grill, and that is an interesting question: why the grill
is an issue about why is it enough to do הגעלה hagalah
and you don't actually need to do ליבון? libun? So I'll just
say this gets discussed in עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, and one of
the answers is is that it was היתרא בלע, heisera bala, that
it absorbed stuff when it absorbed the חטאת chatas taste it was
still היתר. heter. And this gets to an interesting question like kashering
your ovens for פסח Pesach as opposed to kashering your ovens for
like if it was used for טרפות. treifus. I mean the other
day we discussed whether ovens need kashering, but let's assume that you
cooked something actually like the actual gravy dripped on it, it actually
was directly on the grill or whatever the case might be. So
anyway, or frying pan, let's use that, right? So a frying pan
for פסח, Pesach, since the חמץ chametz was היתר heter when it
was initially used, it could be that it does not need the
same degree of kashering. You know, maybe הגעלה hagalah is enough, maybe
something called ליבון קל libun kal is enough. ליבון קל libun kal
is you get it hot enough so that if you were to
touch like a like a paper tissue to it, it would burn.
You know, that's not like a הגעלה hagalah where it gets like,
you know, red hot or something—and not הגעלה, hagalah, excuse me, not
a ליבון libun that it gets ליבון חמור. libun chamur. So anyway,
so that's I'm just mentioning that. That's not a הלכה למעשה, halacha
l'ma'aseh, ask your local Orthodox rabbi, but anyway, but I'm just saying
it's just from here we're going to get to ערב פסח Erev
Pesach when it gets to be ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. I'm just
saying it's interesting why the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* mentions הגעלה hagala *hagalah*
by the grill, and at least one of the reasons given in
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is because it was בולע היתר *bolei heter*
that the stuff it could have absorbed when it was היתר *heter*.
Okay although the גמרא gemara *Gemara* questions that. Now, next משנה mishna,
*Mishnah*. בישל בקדשים ובחולין *Bishal bekodashim vechullin*. Now we are going to
talk about not the ritual of the pot, but a classic כשרות
Kashrus, *kashrus* discussion about you used a pot for something else, what's
the status of the stuff you cooked in it? Okay, and this
is Michael's question, you cooked a שלמים shelamim *shelamim* in your חטאת
chatas. *chatas* pot, right before while does now the שלמים shelamim, *shelamim*
has חטאת chatas *chatas* taste in it? בישל בקדשים ובחולין *Bishal bekodashim
vechullin*. You use the pot for cooking קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* and just
normal food, normal meat. או קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim וקדשים קלים *O
kodshei kodashim vekodashim kalim*, or חטאת chatas *chatas* and a שלמים shelamim
*shelamim*. Okay. אם יש בהן בנותן טעם im yesh bahen benosein taam
*Im yesh bahen benosein ta'am*, if the stuff you cooked has the
taste of the stuff, if it has the taste of the weightier
thing, if the חולין chullin *chullin* has the taste of קדשים Kodashim,
*kodashim* if the שלמים shelamim *shelamim* has the taste of חטאת chatas.
*chatas*, we're going to assume the weightier thing was cooked first. Okay
and the less weightier thing was cooked second. If it gets though
if the taste transferred from the walls into the thing. Now we
all do this by
computation. We all say what's the volume of the walls, is it
1/60th, is it blah blah blah blah blah. But in the משנה
mishna *Mishnah*, the משנה mishna *Mishnah* really wasn't into the computation, it
more was taste it. You can figure it out. Of course if
it's meat and meat, I don't get how you're supposed to be
able to taste it. But the משנה mishna *Mishnah* is not so
much into just quantifying it. Okay, if there's taste that's in the
second thing that you cooked from what was absorbed in the walls,
הרי הקלים נאכלים כחמורים שבהן *harei hakalim ne'echalim kechamurim shebahen*. The lighter
things have to now be treated like the weightier. Okay the שלמים
shelamim *shelamim* has to be treated like a חטאת chatas *chatas*, the
חולין chullin *chullin* has to be treated like a קרבן Korban *korban*
because it has the taste of the קרבן korban *korban* in it,
which means eat it in that zone if it's חולין Chullin *chullin*
that was cooked with a שלמים shelamim. *shelamim* pot don't take it
out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, if it's a שלמים shelamim *shelamim* cooked in
a חטאת chatas *chatas* pot don't take it out of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit Hamikdash*, eat it within that timeframe that's appropriate,
etc. etc. Okay. An interesting question would be what happens which we'll
see if it becomes טמא tamei, *tamei*. I have this חולין Chullin
*chullin* that absorbed שלמים shelamim *shelamim* taste. Is it just שלמים shelamim
*shelamim* from the perspective of food and eating it, and where do
I eat it? If something טמא tamei. *tamei* touches it, if something
טמא Tamei *tamei* touched my חולין Chullin *chullin*, big deal. But if
something טמא Tamei, *tamei* touched my שלמים shelamim *shelamim* I have to
stop eating it. This physical thing like the thing you can see,
the thing you can touch, is חולין Chullin, *chullin* with שלמים shelamim
*shelamim* taste. How much is it like שלמים shelamim. *shelamim* that something
טמא Tamei *tamei* touching it would invalidate it? We'll see about that
in a minute. But the most first immediate assumption is it means
where and when you can eat it and who can eat it.
If it's a שלמים shelamim *shelamim* that absorbed חטאת chatas *chatas* taste
only male כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim* can eat it. Okay. הרי הקלים נאכלים
כחמורים שבהן *harei hakalim ne'echalim kechamurim shebahen*, ואינם טעונים מריקה ושטיפה Merikah
and Sheteifah. *ve'einam te'unim merikah u'shtifah*. Now
you don't have to do מריקה merika ושטיפה *merikah u'shtifah* on the
pot, which is interesting. Well but it would seem like maybe what
it's saying is that this what was a הגעלה hagala, *hagalah*. The
גמרא gemara *Gemara* will ask why not? But one way to read
the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* is when you cooked your שלמים shelamim *shelamim*
in your חטאת chatas *chatas* pot that it achieved a הגעלה hagala
*hagalah*, but okay but at least the next day you'll have to
do מריקה merika ושטיפה *merikah u'shtifah*. Anyway, ואינם פוסלים במגע *ve'einam poslim
bemaga*,
and they don't invalidate through touch, which means the issue I was
dealing with with טומאה tuma *tumah*. That if you touch something טמא
Tamei *tamei* to it it's not a problem. Well why not? Now
it could be for the reason I
said maybe טומאה tuma *tumah* goes by a different measure. The fact
that it has שלמים shelamim, *shelamim* taste in my steak doesn't make
my steak שלמים shelamim. *shelamim*, doesn't mean when I, but who knows?
Okay.
Now,
רקיק שנגע ברקיק וחתיכה בחתיכה *rakik shenaga berakik vechatichah bechatichah*, let's say
you've got like some wafer, a מנחה Mincha, *mincha* wafer that touched
another one or a piece of meat that touched another piece of
meat. לא lo כל הרקיקין ולא כל החתיכות אסורין *lo kol harakikin
velo kol hachatichot asurin*, it doesn't always make it forbidden. אינו אוסר
אלא במקום שבלע *eino oser ela bemakom shebalah*. Okay it's funny it
should have said לא כל החתיכה אסורה *lo kol hachatichah asurah*, because
it could also mean that just touch doesn't always a problem. It
has to be hot enough, it has to be able to absorb,
just a casual touching is not really a problem. But the end
of the משנה *Mishnah* sounds like it's also saying that it only
absorbs in the place that it touched. And therefore it doesn't spread
throughout the entire thing if it's not being cooked together. If it's
touching off of the fire you only have to focus on the
locus of the touch and not on the entire thing. Yes Charlie?
Unless one of these is טמא Tamei *tamei* I don't see a
problem because the מנחה Mincha *mincha*
is מנחה Mincha *mincha* it's the same. But it would be relevant
if one מנחה Mincha, *mincha* was פסול Psul *pasul*, correct. Okay. מאי
קאמר *mai ka'amar*? Now what does this line in the משנה *Mishnah*
mean when it gets to say that oh you don't need מריקה
merika ושטיפה *merikah u'shtifah* and you don't have to worry about touch?
Why not? If it absorbed from weightier thing? So what's it saying?
So here's what it says. חסורי מחסרא, chisorei mechasra. so if you
look at the side, it's pretty ironic, because the side fills in
missing words. The missing words in our גמרא gemara are חסורי מחסרא.
Anyway, חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chisorei mechasra vehachi katani. It's missing some
words and here's how you have to read the משנה. Maybe it's
not ironic. Sometimes people use ironic ironically, it actually means it's very
appropriate. Okay, anyway. אם יש בהן בנותן טעם ta'am it's like when
literally means figuratively. אם יש בהן בנותן טעם הרי הקלים נאכלים כחמורים.
im yesh bahen benosein taam harei hakallim ne'echalim kachamurim. If it gives
off taste, you know, then the weightier stuff absorbed in the walls
of the pot gave up taste to the stuff cooked in the
pot, then the lighter stuff is treated like the weightier stuff. וטעונין
מריקה ושטיפה ute'unin merika ushtifa and now the pot you're cooking in
needs מריקה merika and שטיפה shtifa because now this is like the
weightier thing. ופוסלים במגע uposlim bemaga and yes, טומאה Tumah does apply.
So you have a steak that absorbed שלמים shelamim taste. If somebody
touched that steak, it's now like they, now like you have טמא
שלמים. tamei shelamim. Okay, and therefore it is a problem.
אם אין בהן בנותן טעם, im ein bahen benosein taam, however, if
there is no taste in it,
then אין הקלים נאכלים כחמורים. ein hakallim ne'echalim kachamurim. Then the steak
is not, does not, is not like שלמים, shelamim and the שלמים
shelamim is not like a חטאת. chatas It's nothing. ואין טעונין מריקה
ושטיפה ve'ein te'unin merika ushtifa and now if you went ahead and
cooked that in a different pot I mean this pot itself has
whatever הלכות halachos this pot has, but if you went ahead and
cooked it in a different pot, you wouldn't have to do מריקה
merika and שטיפה shtifa based on the weightier thing, right? Just based
on the thing itself. ואין פוסלים במגע ve'ein poslim bemaga and it
wouldn't have, again, the easier to understand this scenario that you have
a steak cooked in a שלמים Shelamim pot. A steak cooked in
a שלמים Shelamim pot if there's no taste, it doesn't become a
שלמים. Shlamim So you cook this in its own pot now, there's
no requirement of מריקה merika and שטיפה. shtifa. If it becomes טמא,
Tamei it's no problem, etc. So the גמרא gemara smoothes over the
rough edges of the משנה, but it looked at least in theory
that the משנה might be saying something more interesting, like it might
be saying that, you know, even if it gets the weightier status,
you don't need מריקה merika and שטיפה shtifa because you already koshered
it by this cooking of this lighter thing, like the earlier discussion.
And I think the טומאה Tumah idea is a fascinating idea, right?
Like I said, just because something has שלמים Shlamim, juices in it
doesn't mean that when you touch it you've made the שלמים Shlamim
טמא. Tamei, You know, but anyway, but that the גמרא gemara says
yes, you have, the גמרא gemara smoothes over those rough edges. Yes,
Michael.
So it can even be like, you know, I know you were
saying this, like you proxy it by saying a sixtieth, but the
fact like something really spicy can be, it can even be a
lot more to be נותן טעם.
notien taam. Yeah, if the thing itself was spicy, if it wasn't
just that the original thing had a spicy taste because of added
spices, the thing itself would have had to have been spicy. Okay.
נהי דקדשי קדשים לא בעי קדשים קלים ליבעי. nehi dekodshei kodashim lo
ba'ei kodashim kallim lib'ei. So the גמרא gemara says one minute.
So the גמרא's Gemara question is that I understand that the קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim. about it don't, you know, don't have this higher
demands, okay, that they don't need מריקה merika and שטיפה. shtifa. But
the שלמים shelamim, if you cooked your שלמים shelamim in a חטאת
chatas pot, I understand that now this pot doesn't need and either
you cooked it in a different one or going back to our
other point, that was a הגעלה of the חטאת chatas pot. So
I get that this pot doesn't, and it doesn't, the שלמים shelamim,
doesn't have taste of a חטאת. chatas So I understand that the
whole חטאת chatas status has been removed from the pot and it
never entered into the שלמים. shelamim. But what do you mean you
don't need מריקה merika and שטיפה? shtifa? You're still going to need
to do it because you're cooking a שלמים shelamim in this pot,
right? So the גמרא Gemara says, fine.
אמר אביי מאי אין טעונין דקאמר קדשי קדשים אבל קדשים קלים טעונין.
amar Abaye mai ein te'unin deka'amar kodshei kodashim aval kodashim kallim te'unin.
Fine, that's what it means. It means as a חטאת chatas pot
you don't need מריקה merika and שטיפה. shtifa. It now transferred from
a חטאת chatas to a שלמים shelamim, pot. The חטאת Chatas taste
went away, okay, because there wasn't נותן טעם. notien taam. And now
you'll have another day until you need to worry about מריקה merika
and שטיפה. shtifa. Okay, fine. רבא אמר הא מני רבי שמעון היא.
Rava amar ha manni Rabbi Shimon hi. I got a better answer.
Our משנה's going like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, דאמר קדשים קלים אין
טעונין מריקה ושטיפה. de'amar kodashim kallim ein te'unin merika ushtifa. Remember רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon said it's only a הלכה halacha by a חטאת
Chatas. and קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim It doesn't apply to קדשים קלים.
kodashim kallim. So maybe it needs like הגעלה, like that we're not
talking about, but the particular ritual of מריקה and שטיפה shtifa isn't
needed. People remember רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? So therefore, so you cooked
this חטאת Chatas. pot with שלמים, shelamim, that effectively was a הגעלה
on the חטאת Chatas pot. There was no taste of the חטאת
Chatas in the שלמים. shelamim So now the חטאת Chatas disappeared, you
only have שלמים shelamim, here, and according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
no need for מריקה and שטיפה. shtifa. All good. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. בשלמא לרבא היינו דקתני או קדשי
קדשים וקדשים קלים. bishlama leRava hainu dekatani o kodshei kodashim vekodashim kallim.
So for רבא Rava we get why the משנה had two scenarios.
חולין Chullin in a קודש kodesh pot, and שלמים in a חטאת
Chatas pot. Because it wanted to tell us this חידוש chidush that
the שלמים in a חטאת Chatas pot, if there's no taste, you
won't even need to do מריקה and שטיפה shtifa at all, because
it wanted to tell us that we're going like רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. אלא לאביי תרתי למה לי? ela leAbaye tarti lama li? But
according to אביי, Abaye, why do you need two scenarios? חולין and
קודש, kodesh, and קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim, and קדשים קלים? kodashim kallim?
Can't we like infer it since for him really, you know, there's
no new... חידוש Chiddush being added. According to רבא, Rava, the new
חידוש Chiddush by giving us the שלמים scenario is that we rule
like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and that if you're dealing with שלמים
and there's no taste, you don't have to worry about מריקה ושטיפה.
Okay, but according to אביי, Abaye, why two scenarios? So the צריכא,
tzericha, you need both scenarios. דאי תנא קדשים וחולין, De'i tanna Kodashim
veChullin, had he just had that scenario, הוה אמינא חולין הוא דמבטלי
קדשים. hava amina Chullin hu demvatli Kodashim. That's when, if it's חולין
and there's no taste of קדשים, Kodashim that the חולין erase the
קדשים Kodashim, if there's no taste that's retained. Why? דלאו מינייהו, delav
minaihu, because it's not of the same species or genre. So sometimes
the more there's difference, right, the more it eradicates the other thing.
It's just like all חולין here. It eradicates the traces of the
thing that preceded it. Okay, אבל קדשי קדשים וקדשים קלים, Aval Kodashei
Kodashim veKodashim Kalim, אימא לא. eima lo. But if it's two forms
of קדשים, Kodashim maybe I'll sort of say, yeah, cause it's sort
of like רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda principle, מין במינו לא בטיל. min
bemino lo batil. I'll sort of say if you're all within the
קדשים Kodashim, world, the difference isn't stark enough so it doesn't make
the other thing go away. So maybe I would say ביטול bittul
wouldn't be effective in that case. Or I could say the reverse:
ואי תנא קדשי קדשים וקדשים קלים, ve'i tanna Kodashei Kodashim veKodashim Kalim,
הוה אמינא קדשים הוא דאלימי לבוטולי קדשים. hava amina Kodashim hu de'allimi
levatulei Kodashim. I could say the reverse, that when you're dealing with
קדשים, Kodashim קדשים Kodashim, is a very weighty thing. It doesn't go
away so easily. Okay, if you deal with another קדשים, Kodashim that's
strong enough to take it on. Okay, and therefore it'll one קדשים
Kodashim will make another קדשים Kodashim, go away, אבל aval once there's
no taste, חולין, אימא לא, eima lo, but maybe חולין won't have
it, צריכא, tzericha, it needs to tell us that both of them
work. Okay, moving on.
But I would still think it might depend on like, let's say
like the first one was like a lamb, the next one was...
I understand, well that's just a question of נותן טעם. noten ta'am.
But it means even in a scenario when it's not נותן טעם,
noten ta'am, I might think it doesn't go away so easily. Okay.
רק שיחיה ברקיק, Rak sheyichyeh barakik, a wafer touches a wafer. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, כל אשר יגע. Kol asher yiga. It's, now the
תורה Torah says this twice. It says anything that touches the flesh
of a חטאת Chatas יקדש, yikdash, becomes sanctified. And it also says
by a מנחה, Mincha anything that touches it becomes sanctified. What we
learn from that principle is a basic principle of like, again, of
כשרות, that when taste transfers, some of the juices transfer or some
of the מנחה Mincha physically gets absorbed, that when taste transfers, it
affects the thing it transferred into. Now, one way of understanding that
principle is טעם כעיקר, ta'am ke'ikkar, taste is like the thing itself,
right? So you have a drop of chicken soup that falls into
your vegetable soup, and then it's פליישיג. fleishig. You have a drop
of chicken soup that falls into your boiling milk and it's בשר
בחלב. basar bechalav. Okay, or you have a drop of נבילה neveilah
that falls into your טשולנט, cholent, it's all נבילה. neveilah. It's טרייף,
treif, טעם כעיקר. ta'am ke'ikkar. By קדשים, Kodashim it actually might even
be weightier than there. There's a principle called היתר מצטרף לאיסור, heter
mitztaref le'issur, which means that maybe even if you eat just a,
you know, if there's a little bit of טרייף treif for like
a, you know, it may, you know, it makes everything טרייף. treif.
It's not just like, that's a classic question, right? If I have
10% of my chicken soup is נבילה neveilah and I eat a
כזית, kezayit, did I eat a כזית kezayit of נבילה neveilah or
did I eat a tenth of a כזית kezayit of נבילה? neveilah?
Right? You understand the difference. Anyway, so could be by קדשים Kodashim
we say it's, you know, it's like the whole thing got the
identity of the thing being absorbed, whereas by non-קדשים it's just that
you have that proportion that's present, it's not the whole thing became
it. Anyway, but this is the basic principle that we learn from
when it says anything that touches its flesh becomes sanctified, that when
it absorbs from the other thing, it takes on the status of
the thing it absorbed from. Okay, and that's what we're going to
say. כל אשר יגע, Kol asher yiga, יכול אפילו שלא בלע? yachol
afilu shelo bala? Maybe just the act of touching does some affects
the status, even if it didn't absorb, which is what it sounds
like? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, בבשרה, bibsarah, in its flesh. You know,
to get like somehow you really connect deeply, you know, it's like
it's an... so עד שיבלע בבשרה. ad sheyivla bibsarah. So it sounds
like because it speaks about touching the flesh of the thing of
the source, meaning it says X touched a חטאת. Chatas So בבשרה
bibsarah refers to the flesh of the חטאת. Chatas But the way
we're reading it is בבשרה bibsarah is the flesh of X. The
חטאת Chatas went into the בשר basar of X. And therefore that's
what transfers the status of the חטאת chatas to the thing that
touched it. יכול נגע במקצת חתיכה יהיה כולו פסול? Yachol naga bemiktzas
chatichah yiheye kulo pasul? Maybe this gets to the point of the
משנה, where it's not just where it absorbed into X, but the
entire X takes on that status? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, יגע. yiga.
No, it emphasizes the point of contact. הנוגע פסולה. hanogei'a psulah. The
point of contact is where it becomes an issue. הא כיצד? Ha
keitzad? חותך את מקום שבלעה. Chotech es makom shebalah. Okay, if you
can cut away the place point of contact, then the rest of
it remains okay. All right, so we learn number one: only if
there's a real transfer of juices, which is then becomes the basis
like I said for principles about cooking things together and טעם and
the whole thing. Okay, but if it's not on a fire, it's
touching off the fire, it just got absorbed, then the absorption is
local. If it's over a fire, the fire spreads it. But if
it's not over a fire, the absorption is local and just take
it away.
Now, הא כיצד? Ha keitzad? We did that. בבשרה, bibsarah, its flesh,
ולא בגידין. velo vegiddin. Now הכיצד, Hakeitzad, we did that. בבשרה, Bivsara,
its flesh, ולא בגידין, v'lo bigidin, ולא בעצמות, v'lo b'atzamot, ולא בקרנים,
v'lo b'karnayim, ולא בטלפין. v'lo b'tlafin. So presumably now we're talking not
about X but about the חטאת chatas or the source. It's only
the flesh which transfers taste and the flesh which has the status.
The horns and the hooves and whatever, that doesn't have any special
halakhic status. So that and also it's how do you transfer taste
of a horn? But anyway, by touch. So that's not what we're
referring to. Okay, יקדש, Yikdash, so now X becomes holy, להיות כמוה,
lihyot kamoah, it takes on the status of the חטאת chatas or
whatever that קרבן korban. was that was the source, the source.
הכיצד, Hakeitzad, what does this mean? אם פסולה היא תפסל, Im psulah
hi tipaseil, so that normally wouldn't be the first thing we would
say יקדש Yikdash means, but holiness often means that it's more vulnerable,
it's to be somehow become invalid or to have problems, to being
off-limits and so on. So if the חטאת Chatas. was invalid and
touched a שלמים that was valid or like whatever your name is,
Charlie said, why what does it mean a מנחה Mincha, touches a
מנחה, Mincha all מנחות Minchos are קדשי קדשים, so what but if
one מנחה Mincha was invalid and touched a מנחה mincha. that was
valid, now the new מנחה, mincha. the receiving מנחה mincha. also becomes
invalid unless you remove the area of transfer.
Okay, would it be a liquid connected like
in טומאה Tumah, or not?
No, it just has to be physically there has to be some
transfer of some of the juices, some of the thing from the
source has to transfer into the receiving thing. So
if it's just like they're cold and there's not and whatever and
they're just touching on the surface, you rinse it off, you're fine.
If it's right, if it's porous and there are juices or whatever
and then it gets absorbed, so it's all just a physical assessment
of what physically transferred in. Yeah.
Yeah, so a language question here, so in טומאה Tumah and טומאה,
Tumah something that is טמא Tamei can cause something else to be
טמא, Tamei but when we use the word פסולה, Psulah, it implies
that it is not usable, but it can't make something else?
But it's not making it, maybe that's also what David was asking,
it's not making it טמא Tamei. by laws of טומאה Tumah that
when A touches B the טומאה Tumah, transfers from A to B,
but it goes down a level and if it's only if B
has been in contact with water and is הוכשר לקבל טומאה huchshar
l'kabeil Tumah whatever, that's not what happens. It's not that, no no,
but here's the point. It's not that A stays A and B
stays B, but the טומאה Tumah, transferred and went down a level.
Okay, what happened is that little pieces of A sort of penetrated
into B. So B now is פסול Psul because it has טמא
tamei, A in it, פסול Psul A inside of B. It's not
that A's touching of B transferred טומאה, it's that when there was
absorption you now have little parts of A inside of B. Okay,
and if A was פסול Psul because it was a טמא מנחה,
Tamei Mincha, then you can't eat B because you have pieces of
a טמא מנחה Tamei Mincha inside of B. B isn't טמא tamei.
it just necessarily, depends on the cases, but it just have pieces
of טמא tamei. stuff in it and that's the problem. Okay, so
it's not about the transfer of טומאה, it's about the physical transfer
of the object itself. Alright. הכיצד, Hakeitzad, אם פסולה
היא תפסל, im psulah hi tipaseil, if it's if A was פסול
Psul then B becomes פסול again because it has pieces of A
in it. ואם כשרה, V'im ksheirah, and if A was כשר, Kosher,
then היא תאכל כחמור שבה. hi teiacheil k'chamur shebah. But let's say
it has a weightier status. A is a חטאת chatas and B
is a שלמים, okay, or A is a חטאת chatas and B
is just a normal steak. So now because B has parts, some
חטאת chatas. absorbed in it, you have to treat B as a
חטאת chatas, even though really it is a שלמים or just a
normal steak. And that's יקדש, Yikdash, it gets on the higher status
of the thing that it transferred into it. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara has a question, אמאי, Amai, now why is this? Why
is it that you cannot you have to eat B if
let me see how to say
if
let's say the case that A is invalid, okay, and it got
absorbed into B. And it's not invalid because it's נותר. Nosar. נותר
Nosar is כרת. Kares. Let's say A was טמא, tamei something טמא
touched A. Okay, and now pieces of A got absorbed into B.
So מנחה טמאה Mincha Tmeiah got absorbed, which is A, got absorbed
into a non-טמא מנחה Tamei Mincha B. So what we have to
say is you can't eat any of B, gotta throw it all
out or whatever, burn it, etc., because it has pieces of A
absorbed into it. And since you can't eat A you can't eat
B, right, that's what we said. But the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, ninety-eight percent of B is a כשר מנחה, Kosher Mincha, right?
And there's a מצוה Mitzvah to eat a כשר מנחה. Kosher Mincha.
So why doesn't the מצוה Mitzvah to eat a כשר מנחה Kosher
Mincha override the fact that there's two percent of stuff in here
that's not allowed to be eaten? When it comes to A itself,
as soon as A is טמא there's no longer a מצוה Mitzvah
to eat A, right? Because A is טמא. But B is ninety-eight
percent totally a valid מנחה mincha. and a מצוה Mitzvah to eat
it. So just because I have... little 2% of טרייף traife stuff
mixed up, or you know, why shouldn't the מצוה mitzvah to eat
A override the prohibition of eating the little pieces of B that
are in it?
Is this a general rule that לא תעשה lo ta'aseh is more
powerful?
No, an עשה aseh overrides a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh if there's
no way to do both of them to avoid the conflict. And
there's no way to avoid the conflict here. Right? I mean, yes,
if I could cut away the piece then that's fine. But let's
say it's spread throughout or something. There's no way to avoid the
conflict. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. says, okay, וניתי עשה, veneisei aseh,
right, ולידחי לא תעשה? velidchi lo ta'aseh? Why not? Okay, go ahead
and eat B. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אין עשה דוחה לא תעשה
שבמקדש. ein aseh docheh lo ta'aseh shebamikdash. No, in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash those laws don't apply. Okay, the עשה דוחה לא תעשה
aseh docheh lo ta'aseh doesn't apply.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it says,
ועצם לא תשברו בו. ve'etzem lo tishberu vo. Don't break a bone
in a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. ורבי שמעון בן
מנסיא אומר, VeRabbi Shimon ben Menasya omer, אחד עצם שיש בו מוח
ואחד עצם שאין בו מוח. echad etzem sheyesh bo moach ve'echad etzem
she'ein bo moach. Whether it has marrow or doesn't have marrow, the
תורה Torah is categorical, you're not allowed to break a bone.
אמאי? Amai? Now we can ask, why are you not allowed to
break a bone if it's got marrow in it? ניתי עשה ולידחי
לא תעשה. Neisei aseh velidchi lo ta'aseh. Let the עשה aseh of
eating the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach override the לא תעשה lo ta'aseh
of breaking a bone. אלא אין עשה דוחה לא תעשה שבמקדש. Ela
ein aseh docheh lo ta'aseh shebamikdash. From here we infer that it
does not override in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. and that's the
answer here. Now of course there it's also a little different because
you violate the לא תעשה lo ta'aseh before you get around to
the עשה, aseh, right? First you break the bone and then you
eat the meat. Okay, and also תוספות Tosafos points out there's ways
of getting to the meat without eating the bone, like without breaking
the bone. You could put the bone near a fire and let
it break by itself. So there they're not directly at loggerheads. If
they're not directly coming at the same time and at loggerheads, you
wouldn't say override. Here they are directly at loggerheads. There's no way
of eating B without eating the little pieces of A that are
absorbed into it. Okay, but nevertheless, answer number one is that even
though there's no way around it and it would come at the
same time, we don't say עשה דוחה לא תעשה aseh docheh lo
ta'aseh in the בית המקדש.
So that would mean that any טמא קרבן? tamei korban?
No, once the קרבן korban itself is טמא, the מצוה mitzvah to
eat it goes away. But here the point is, so A of
course you don't eat because it's no longer a מצוה mitzvah to
eat A because it's טמא. But B, there's still a מצוה mitzvah
to eat. That's why I said B isn't טמא. 98% B is
totally טהור. tahor. It's just got little pieces of A mixed into
it. Okay, so רב
אשי אמר,
Rav Ashi
amar, יקדש עשה הוא. Yikdash aseh hu. No, when the פסוק pasuk
tells you you have to treat B like A, כל אשר יגע
בבשרה יקדש, kol asher yiga bivsarah yikdash, that means that you have
a מצות עשה mitzvas aseh to treat B with the status of
A. So therefore your obligation to eat B doesn't override, A, the
prohibition of eating a טמא קרבן, tamei korban, which is one thing
it has to contend with, and B, it would go against your
positive מצוה mitzvah to be treating B as if it were A.
Right? You got it? So that הלכה halacha that when it absorbs
A, when B absorbs A you got to treat B as if
it's A, is itself a מצוה, mitzvah, it's not just a description
of the הלכה halachic status. Okay. יקדש
עשה הוא. Yikdash aseh hu. ואין עשה דוחה לא תעשה ועשה. ve'ein
aseh docheh lo ta'aseh ve'aseh. And therefore it can't override the negative
prohibition of eating טמא A and the positive מצוה mitzvah of treating
B as if it were A. Okay. Now that's
the so that's the end of that discussion about why not say
the עשה aseh overrides the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. Now we're going
to talk about that the תורה Torah only says this by a
חטאת chatat and a מנחה. mincha How do we know to apply
it more broadly? And this is going to be a fascinating little
discussion because it's going to go well beyond this issue about transfer
of taste and talk about in general how we know principles that
apply to some קרבנות korbanos. apply to all the קרבנות. korbanos? So
let's take a look. Okay.
אשכחן חטאת דמקדש בבלוע. Ashkan chatas demikdash bevalu'a. We found that the
תורה Torah says that a חטאת transfers its status by being absorbed
into something else. שאר קדשים מנלן? Sha'ar kodashim minalan? Where do you
know it by other
קרבנות? korbanos, אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, משום רבי אלעזר, mishum Rabbi Elazar,
וזאת התורה לעולה ולמנחה ולחטאת ולאשם ולמילואים ולזבח השלמים. Vezos hatorah la'olah
velamincha velachatas vela'asham velamilu'im ulezevach hashelamim. The תורה Torah has a nice
little פסוק pasuk there saying this is the law and when it
ends צו, Tzav, it went through all the קרבנות, korbanos. wraps it
all up. Wonderful. That's a very beautiful poetic coda. Okay, but the
גמרא Gemara, says you got to learn something from it. And what
we're going to learn is, if it puts it all under this
umbrella of וזאת התורה, vezos hatorah, that means that some הלכות halachos
that we know only about that we only know about in one
of these cases really can now be learned to apply to all
these all these קרבנות. korbanos? And now we're going to go through
them. לעולה, La'olah, the עולה. olah. So what are we going to
apply from עולה olah to all other קרבנות? korbanos כעולה, Ke'olah, other
things are just like an
עולה, olah, כעולה ke'olah mean like כעולה. ke'olah. מה עולה טעונה כלי
אף כל טעונה כלי. Mah olah te'unah keli af kol te'unah keli.
The same way by an עולה olah when you שחט shacht it,
you need a כלי, keli, by everything else when you שחט shacht
it you need a כלי. keli. Now there's an interesting debate of
רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafos. Does כלי *kli* mean a כלי שרת
*kli sharet*? Does the knife, right, remember, שחיטה shechita *shechita* does not
have to be by a כהן *kohen*, right?
So, and does the knife and the כהן *kohen* guy that who
does the שחיטה shechitah *shechita* or even the gal, don't even have
to stand in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*? The animal has to
be in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, they can even stand outside.
So does the knife have to be a כלי שרת *kli sharet*
if the שוחט *shochet* doesn't have to be a כהן *kohen* and
the שוחט *shochet* can stand outside the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*? So
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, yes, that's what we're learning, that the knife
does have to be a כלי שרת *kli sharet*, but תוספות *Tosfos*
has an opinion that no, it's כלי *kli* means it has to
be something that is fashioned. You can't go ahead and take something
just part of the natural world, take like a nice reed that
has a sharp edge and use it as your שחיטה *shechita* knife.
Okay, it has to actually be something that is man-made, it has
to be fashioned, it has to be a כלי *kli*, but it
might not mean that it has to be a כלי שרת *kli
sharet*. Okay, so that's a very interesting question, right, whether the whether
the שחיטה *shechita* knife has to be a כלי שרת *kli sharet*
or not. Okay, but it does have to be at least a
vessel, okay, something fashioned. מה עולה Olah טעונה כלי אף כל טעונה
כלי *ma ola teuna kli af kol teuna kli*. מאי כלי *mai
kli*? What do you mean by כלי *kli*? אילימא מזרק *ilima mizrak*,
if you mean the bowl that you catch the blood in, so
we
that you don't need to learn that from an עולה olah, *ola*.
בשלמי ציבור נמי כתיב בהו *beshalmei tzibur nami kesiv behu*. You learn
it from one of the first קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* in the תורה
Torah *Torah*, well, the first קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* that they had as
a nation, the שלמים *shlamim* that they brought at the foot of
הר סיני *Har Sinai*. ויקח משה חצי הדם וישם באגנת *vayakach Moshe
chatzi hadam vayasem ba'aganot*, okay, and therefore, and you know, we should
be learning from there and that's maybe an earlier paradigm and so
on. So we can't just be talking about the vessel of catching
the blood, that's too obvious and we know that from other places.
אלא דסכין *ela desakin*. Okay, so I jumped ahead. Okay, we mean
the actual שחיטה *shechita* knife, that has to be a כלי *kli*
and maybe even a כלי שרת *kli sharet*. ועולה גופא מנא לן
*v'ola gufa mna lan*? All right, it's very nice, where do you
know that from an עולה *ola*? So דכתיב *dechesiv*, this is such
a sort of I don't know disturbing or hair-raising גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
וישלח אברהם את ידו ויקח את המאכלת vayakach es hama'acheles *vayishlach Avraham
es yado vayikach es hamachelet*. Okay, we learn it from עקידת יצחק
Yitzchak, *Akeidas Yitzchak*, okay, because it describes it with this word את
המאכלת *es hamachelet*,
which, you know, I once heard a שיעור *shiur* on עקידת יצחק
Yitzchak, *Akeidas Yitzchak* from, I think it was אוריאל סימון *Uriel Simon*,
right, Simon, very famous Bible scholar in Israel, anyway, and he said
the only place in the תורה Torah *Torah* where it uses the
this word מאכלת *machelet* to describe a knife, the only place is
in, you know, is in עקידת יצחק *Akeidas Yitzchak*. You know, and
you think about it, right, if the word מאכלת *machelet* is like
meat-eater, you know, it's like it describes like the horror of thinking
about the knife, right, you know, and like what, you know, sort
of like looking at it from יצחק's *Yitzchak's* perspective. Anyway, somehow we're
learning from the fact that it says that it doesn't say he
tried to שחט shecht *shecht* his son, it emphasizes he took the
knife to שחט *shecht* his son, the focus on the knife tells
us, you know, that you need this כלי *kli*. Of course, again,
looking at this through יצחק's *Yitzchak's* eyes, right, you know, you see
the knife coming at you, right? Okay, ויקח את המאכלת *vayikach es
hamachelet*, והתם עולה הוא *v'hasam ola hu*, and יצחק *Yitzchak* was an
עולה *ola*, דכתיב ויעלהו לעולה תחת בנו *dechesiv vaya'alehu l'ola tachas bno*.
So we say, I mean, it's interesting that it didn't actually say
that what do you call it, it didn't actually say that God
said to אברהם *Avraham*, right, והעלהו שם לעולה על אחד ההרים *v'ha'alehu
sham l'ola al achad heharim*. It speaks about the ram that's offered
in its place, right, which maybe actually is, you know, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara's* softening this, right? Maybe the גמרא *Gemara's* at the end
saying, right, why didn't it say יצחק *Yitzchak* was the עולה *ola*?
And because at the end the ram was the עולה *ola*, and
maybe in the end what we're saying is we're learning it from
the ram that was brought in יצחק's *Yitzchak's* place. That was an
עולה *ola*, we're not learning it from יצחק *Yitzchak*. That would be
so deeply disturbing, right? But again, the idea that this took place
on הר הבית *Har Habayis*, you know, that the מזבח *mizbe'ach* corresponds
to the מזבח *mizbe'ach* above and that there's this this whole מדרש
*Midrash* that the מזבח *mizbe'ach* above has like the ashes of יצחק
*Yitzchak* on them, the idea that אברהם *Avraham* maybe actually went through
with it, you know, and then there was a תחיית המתים *techiyas
hameisim*, there's that idea in the מדרשים *Midrashim*, you know, so the
idea about how thinking about how sacrifices could be a substitute for
this more, you know, sort of pagan, you know, sort of impetus
of actual child sacrifice, and that was maybe the whole lesson of
עקידת יצחק *Akeidas Yitzchak*, God doesn't want humans, right, wants we're going
to use the animal sacrifice as a substitute. Okay, but this sort
of brings all of that to the surface, right, and makes that
association. So to think that how we שחט *shecht* every single day
when we're שוחט *shechting* a sacrifice in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*,
are we basing ourselves on the model of עקידת יצחק *Akeidas Yitzchak*
is somehow deeply disturbing, but it could be that at the last
minute what the גמרא *Gemara* is doing is it's shifting, no, no,
no, we're basing ourselves on the on the ram that was brought
in its place. We're not basing ourselves on יצחק *Yitzchak*. So it
doesn't say יצחק *Yitzchak* was an עולה *ola*. It says that the
ram was the עולה *ola*. That's what we're basing ourselves on. So
it's a very interesting powerful dynamic going on here. Yes, Charlie?
Earlier in that narrative there is the language for the... והעלהו שם
לעולה.
That's what I said. I said that. I said and it's interesting
that the גמרא is not choosing the עולה word used to describe
יצחק, right? It's even though the scene, ויקח את המאכלת is יצחק,
when it ultimately gets to say the basis of עולה, it shifts
to the ram. So, you know, it's like a, it's a pretty
like, you know, tense גמרא. Yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, yeah. So
anyway, so, okay. Now, מנחה. mincha, Now, moving on to מנחה. mincha.
So after that hugely powerful גמרא, it's like I need a drink
after that. Like anyway. Just, let's just move on. Okay. That's a
nice שחיטה knife. Next thing.
I think the horse talks to meat today that had to die
to make that witness.
Anyway, there you go. Next thing. מנחה. mincha מה מנחה אינה נאכלת
אלא לזכרי כהונה אף כל אינן נאכלין אלא לזכרי כהונה. Mah mincha
eina ne'echeles ela l'zichrei kehuna af kol einan ne'echalin ela l'zichrei kehuna.
So the same way מנחה's mincha. only eaten for male כהנים, kohanim.
the same is true about all of these. Now, it's actually interesting,
right? Because if all of these, if זבח שלמים zevach shelamim means
like a, what do you call it? Like a שלמי ציבור, shalmei
tzibur, that's true. שלמי ציבור's shalmei tzibur only eaten by male כהנים.
kohanim, Okay. It's not all קרבנות korbanos. are only by male כהנים,
kohanim. but maybe it's what it's saying is the default is male
כהנים. kohanim. With the exception of שלמים, the default of all קרבנות
korbanot, is male כהנים. kohanim. Okay. So then the גמרא says, now
why do I need to tell me that? Like, it says it
by every קרבן. korban So מאי היא? mai hee? אי חטאת ואשם
בהדיא כתיב בהו. Ee chatas v'asham b'hedya kesiv behu. If it's a
חטאת and an אשם, asham, I don't need to learn it from
מנחה, it says it explicitly. Okay. כל זכר בכהנים יאכלנה. Kol zachar
bakohanim yochlenah. ואי שלמי ציבור, v'ee shalmei tzibur, if it's a שלמים
that's a communal שלמים, מבי דקרא אתי. mibei d'kra asi. I learn
it from the extra פסוק pasuk where it says by קרח Korach
where it says all the things that are given to the כהנים.
kohanim It says, בקודש הקודשים תאכלנו כל זכר יאכל אותו. B'kodesh hakodashim
tochalenu kol zachar yochal oso. So there's this extra wrap-up verse, all
males eat it. Okay. And we say what does that extra verse
in קרח Korach do saying all male כהנים kohanim. eat it? לימד
על שלמי ציבור שאינם נאכלים אלא לזכרי כהונה. Limmed al shalmei tzibur
she'einam ne'echalim ela l'zichrei kehuna. The only thing we don't know, the
one קרבן korban. we don't know what the story is, is this
communal שלמים. Okay. And that פסוק pasuk teaches you in קרח Korach
that it's eaten by male כהנים. So you don't need to learn
it from a מנחה. That's the one קרבן korban that we need
to know what it is, but you don't need to learn it
from a מנחה here in צו, Tzav, you can learn it from
the פסוק pasuk over there in קרח. Korach. So the גמרא says
תנאי היא. Tanna'ei hi. It's a debate of תנאים Tannaim where we
learn it from. Okay. איכא דנפקא ליה מהכא ואיכא דנפקא ליה מהכא.
Ika d'nafka lei mehacha v'ika d'nafka lei mehacha. Fine. So, you know,
that's not going to make me lose sleep at night. At the
end of the day, we agree to the הלכה. halacha. The question
is, which פסוק pasuk do you learn it from? So some learn
it from the פסוק pasuk in קרח, Korach, we're learning it here
from the פסוק pasuk by a מנחה. Okay. Let's just do a
little bit more.
חטאת. So we got לעולה ולמנחה, l'olah u'l'mincha, now it's ולחטאת. v'lachatas.
מה חטאת מתקדשת בבלוע אף כל מתקדשת בבלוע. Mah chatas miskadeshes b'valu'a
af kol miskadeshes b'valu'a. That's what, why we brought this up. Okay.
The same way when a חטאת gets absorbed into something, the thing
that received the חטאת takes on the status of the חטאת. So
this is true about any קרבן. korban, If any קרבן korban gets
absorbed into something, the thing that receives it takes on the status,
you know, of the thing that got absorbed. Okay. And that's why
we quoted all of this. אשם. Asham. So okay, that's
זאת התורה לעולה ולמנחה ולחטאת ולאשם. zos hatorah l'olah u'l'mincha u'l'chatas u'l'asham.
So what's the אשם? asham? מה אשם אין שפיר ושליא קדוש בו
אף כל אין שפיר ושליא קדוש בו. Mah asham ein shapir v'shilya
kadosh bo af kol ein shapir v'shilya kadosh bo. So an אשם
asham is male. Okay. Because an אשם asham is male, you don't
have
any fetuses in its womb. Okay. So because it doesn't have a
womb. So therefore we can learn, oh, so you know what you
know about an אשם? asham? That if you sanctified an אשם, asham,
you would never have to be מקריב makriv as the fats or
whatever, the fetuses. You know how you know that? Because there wouldn't
be any fetuses. Fine. But since that's true, we can now apply
that principle to female קרבנות korbanot. and say that if you brought
something that's like a שלמים that's female, right, or a חטאת, and
it happens to have a fetus inside of it, the fetus is
now treated as חלב chelev and you don't put it on the
altar. Okay. So, so אף כל אין
שפיר ושליא קדוש בו. af kol ein shapir v'shilya kadosh bo. קסבר,
Kasavar, he's of the opinion, ולדות קדשים בהווייתן הן קדושים, vladot kodashim
b'havayasan hen kedoshim, that fetuses of sacrifices only become sanctified
when they're born, not in their mother's womb. So this is all
interesting questions. Does it mean they're not sanctified at all? Does it
mean just that they don't become treated like the חלב chelev to
be put on the altar? Okay. But anyway, but somehow we learn
from an אשם asham that the same way obviously there's no fetuses,
so there's no special status to the fetuses, that is true even
by animals that do have fetuses. Okay.
ודנים, V'danim, here's I think answering your question, אפשר משאי אפשר. efshar
mishe'ee efshar. And this is, would be of the opinion that you
can learn out something possible from something impossible. Even though, even though
it's not relevant to an אשם, asham, it never happens, but nevertheless,
it's a hermeneutic principle that the absence of it from an אשם
asham allows you to say that it's also absent from other קרבנות.
korbanot Don't ask
me. Okay. מלואים, miluim, okay לא לעלה ולמנחה ולחטאת ולאשם ולמלואים ולזבח
השלמים. le-olah ve-la-minchah ve-la-chatat ve-la-asham ve-la-miluim u-le-zevach ha-shelamim. מה מלואים מותרותיהם בשריפה.
mah miluim mostroseihem bisreifah. Now what's a שריפה sreifah by מלואים? miluim?
Because it says by the מלואים, miluim, it says when the פסוק
pasuk speaks about the מלואים miluim קרבנות, korbanot you know that they
bring, it says if any of the meat is left over to
the next morning, נותר באש תשרוף nosar ba-esh tisrof or burn it.
Okay, fine, so if it's left over you burn it. We sort
of know that by all קרבנות. korbanot. No, but the point is
the next part. ואין בעלי חיים במותרותיהם. ve-ein baalei chayim bemostroseihem. Again,
this is a type of an אפשר משאי אפשר. efshar mi-she-ee-efshar. The
תורה Torah never has a scenario, this is a real like fetch,
the תורה never has a scenario where you have a קרבן, korban
a living קרבן korban that is left over. What does that mean?
What's a living קרבן korban, that's left over? So רש"י so an
example would be I sanctify one קרבן korban and then I sanctify
another one as a backup. Or I sanctify one קרבן, korban I
lose it, and so I sanctified another one and I brought the
other one and then I found the first one. So here's a
question. Since all of that, that backup or that second one, is
a sort of an expansion of the קדושה kedusha of the first
one, conceptually it's linked to the first, I might think why don't
I call it נותר? nosar? The same way after I bring the
first one and שחט it, meat that's left over an extra day
is נותר nosar and I have to burn it, maybe if another
animal, a living animal was sanctified as a type of a backup
or whatever, maybe it also becomes נותר nosar after the next day?
Maybe I have to burn even the living animal because it's now
it's, you know, it's it's it's no longer
usable, the actual original קרבן was brought, let me call this נותר
nosar and burn it. So it says no. The same way you
never had that by מלואים. miluim. Again, this is more like an
לא היה lo haya case. The same way by מלואים miluim it
spoke about leftover meat, but it never addressed the case of a
living animal, so the implicit point by מלואים miluim would be either
they didn't have it or the implicit point would be if it
were a living animal there wouldn't be a concept of נותר. nosar.
So we apply that to other things as well. אף כל מותרותיהם
בשריפה, af kol mostroseihem bisreifah, by everything else I say the נותר
nosar is burnt, which is usually explicit in the פסוק, pasuk, ואין
בעלי חיים במותרותיהם ve-ein baalei chayim bemostroseihem but the real point is
you don't apply נותר nosar to a living animal even if it
was a backup or somehow connected to the one that was brought.
And then the last thing. So we did לעלה le-olah שחיטה knife,
ולמנחה ve-la-minchah מילואי כהנים. milui kohanim. Okay, ולעלה ולמנחה ולחטאת ve-la-olah ve-la-minchah
ve-la-chatat absorbing into something
else, ולעלה ולמנחה ולחטאת ולאשם, ve-la-olah ve-la-minchah ve-la-chatat ve-la-asham, אשם asham is
the thing about not sanctifying the fetuses, ולמלואים, ve-la-miluim, okay, which is
this idea you don't say נותר nosar by a living animal, ולזבח
השלמים u-le-zevach ha-shelamim last one. Okay. So what's זבח השלמים? zevach ha-shelamim?
שלמים, מה שלמים מפגלין ומתפגרין, mah shelamim mapgilin u-mitpagrin, never get away
from פיגול. piggul. So the תורה talks about פיגול piggul by a
שלמים, so the same way by שלמים there's an idea of פיגול,
piggul, both it causes פיגול piggul when you're doing the דם dam
and you're doing the עבודה avodah of the שלמים, that thought that
you have during that thing makes the meat into פיגול piggul and
it becomes פיגול. piggul. אף כל מפגלין ומתפגרין. af kol mapgilin u-mitpagrin.
So also all other קרבנות korbanot. the concept of פיגול piggul is
a relevant concept by other קרבנות as well. So that's what we
learn from זאת התורה zot ha-torah to apply these principles we know
by one קרבן to all the קרבנות. We started by the חטאת
and the absorption, but now we learn that it applies in, you
know, a lot of other הלכות halachot that are shared by all
these קרבנות.
And we've been doing
that.